Register of the Joaquin Maurin Papers, 1870-1976
Hoover Institution Archives
- SUBJECT FILE, 1870-1973
  - Partido Obrero de Unificacion Marxista (P.O.U.M.). See also Alba, Victor; Orwell, George and CORRESPONDENCE, P.O.U.M.
    - General, 1947-1971 (mostly newsletters by the Executive Committee and correspondence between members)
    - Letter of Maurin to Joan Rocabert, dated Oct. 11, 1971, stating his position on the party and his political beliefs in general
    - Meeting, Jan. 5, 1936 (newspaper accounts)
    - Printed material, 1936-1947
  - Paul y Angulo, Jose
  - Perez Solis, Oscar. See also Spain, Communism
  - Perezagua, Facundo
  - Pestana, Angel. See Spain, Politics, 1930s
  - Portugal. "Comment les Communistes ont Essaye de s'Emparer du Pouvoir au Portugal" (supplement of Est-Ouest), 1975
  - Puerto Rico
  - Replica, Puerto Rico, 1973
  - Rio, Angel de
    - General
    - "The Equivoco of Don Quixote", 1962. Printed copy of an essay
  - Rios, Fernando de los. See United States, Articles in the foreign press, 1929
  - Robles, Amadeo. See Partido Obrero de Unificacion Marxista
  - Robleto, Hernan
  - Rosarios, Ottocar
  - Salvochea y Alvarez, Fermin
  - Scales, Junius (petition for), 1961
  - Sedov, Leon (letter to Jeanne Maurin, dated March 2, 1937 )
  - Sender, Ramon J. See also Bowers, Claude and Weil, Simone
  - Serge, Victor. See also Spain, Catalonia, May Events and BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Articles on Maurin
  - Sierra Berdecia, Fernando
  - Socialism
    - Europe (post-war)
    - United States (post-war)
    - Newspaper reprints of photographs or sketches of famous socialist leaders of different countries
  - Solari, Juan Antonio
  - Souvarine, Boris. See also CORRESPONDENCE, Araquistain, Luis
  - Soviet Union, 1933-1963. See also Babel, Isaak
  - Space exploration
  - Spain (Box 28)
    - General
    - The agrarian question
      - Malefakis, Edward E.: "The Agrarian Problem and the Republic". Type-written copy of a talk delivered at the AHA Convention, 1966
      - Minlos, L. V.: "Hombres sin tierras, tierras sin hombres", n.d. Printed copy
    - Anticlericalism - The "Semana Tragica", 1909. See also Ferrer Guardia, Francisco and CORRESPONDENCE, Connelly Ullman, Joan
    - Asturias rebellion, Oct. 1934
    - Basque nationalism
    - Catalonia
      - General
      - Anarchism, 1911 (album of photographs and names of anarchists, Barcelona)
      - Autonomy statute, 1931
      - Elections
        - 1932
        - 1936
      - First Workers Congress, Barcelona, 1870 (article on)
      - May Events of Barcelona, 1937
      - Socialist movement of Catalonia. Manifesto, 1972
    - Civil war (bibliography)
    - Communism. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and Naturalization process, Documents submitted and CORRESPONDENCE, Portela, Luis
    - Constitution, 1931
    - Economy, 1930s
    - Franco's Spain
      - General
      - Articles by
        - Theodore White
        - James K. Williams
    - Government in exile in Mexico. See CORRESPONDENCE, Just, Julio
    - History
      - General
      - 1st of May celebrations, 19th and 20th centuries
    - Labor movement
      - General
      - Strikes
    - Literature (bibliography)
    - Politics, 1930s
    - Refugees of the civil war
    - Socialist party. See CORRESPONDENCE, Grossi-Mier, Manuel
    - Tourism
  - Spanish Sahara, 1969
  - Stassen, Harold
  - Stevenson, Adlai
  - Thomas, Hugh
  - Thomas, Norman. See also Socialism, United States and Scales, Junius
  - Los Tiempos, Bolivia, 1969
  - Torralva Beci, Eduardo
  - Trotsky, Leon (including an original hand-written letter to the P.O.U.M., Oct. 1936, expressing his grief over the announcement of Maurin's presumed death)
  - Truman, Harry S.
  - Ugarte, Manuel
  - Unamuno, Miguel de
  - Union Socialista Espanola. Pamphlet, June 1960
  - United Fruit Company
  - United Nations, N.Y. (list of permanent missions and delegations to the United Nations, May 1954 )
  - United States
    - General
    - Articles in the foreign press, 1929
    - Economy
    - Labor movement. See Hillman, Sidney
    - New York
      - General. See also Mailer, Norman Harlem
  - Untermann, Ernest
  - Uslar Pietri, Arturo
  - Viladrich Vila, Miguel
  - Villeda Morales, Ramon
  - Voz Obrera (Accion Comunista), 1973
  - Ward, Barbara: "The silent revolution", n.d. Printed copy
  - Weil, Simone
  - World War, 1939-1945
  - Wright, Richard
  - Yale Alumni Fund 1952 Campaign
  - Miscellanea (Box 29)
    - General, (2 folders)
    - "Estampas de la Revolucion Espanola, 19 Julio de 1936 " (31 reproductions of watercolors by the artist Sim, published by the Offices of Propaganda of the CNT-FAI)
    - Madrid, Barcelona, 1937 (pamphlet containing reproductions of photographs of the bombing of Madrid)
- NEWSPAPERS, 1919-1976
  - Accion Sindicalista, Valencia. 1922, Aug. 10, 18; Sept. 1, 8, 15, 22, 29; Oct. 6, 13, 20, 27; Nov. 4, 11, 18, 23; Dec. 2, 9 (Box 30)
  - El Amigo del Pueblo (Los Amigos de Durruti), Barcelona. 1937, July 20
  - La Antorcha (Partido Comunista de Espana), Madrid. 1924, Nov. 21, 28; Dec. 5, 12, 19, 26; 1925, Aug. 7, 28; Sept. 4, 11; Nov. 27; 1926, Jan. 22, 29
  - Avanti! (Partito Socialista Italiano), Paris. 1937, May 16
  - La Batalla. See Apendix to register
  - CNT (Confederacion Nacional del Trabajo), Mexico. July 1956 (two copies); May-June 60
  - El Comunista (Federacion Levantina del P.O.U.M.), Valencia. 1936, Sept. 12, 19, 26; Oct. 3, 10, 17, 24
  - Espana Libre (CNT-AIT), Toulouse. 1960, March; June; October
  - Espana Libre (Sociedades Hispanas Confederadas de los Estados Unidos), New York. 1962, Feb. 16; April 20; 1966, Jan.; 1968, March-April; 1976, March-April
  - Front (Joventut Comunista Iberica - P.O.U.M.), Sitges. 1936, Nov. 1, 8, 15, 22, 29
  - Le Journal de Barcelone, Paris, 1937, April 16, 30
  - Juventud Comunista (Joventut Comunista Iberica P.O.U.M.), Banos Nuevos. 1937, March 11, 18, 25; April 1; June 3
  - Lucha Obrera, Barcelona. 1923, Dec. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30; 1924, Jan. 1
  - Lucha Social (Federacion Local Obrera), Lerida (Box 31)
    - 1919, Oct. 4, 11, 18, 25; Nov. 1, 8, 15, 22 (two copies), 29; Dec. 6, 14
    - 1920, April 17, 24; May 1, 8, 15, 22, 29; June 5, 12, 19, 26; July 3, 10, 17, 24, 31; Aug. 7, 14, 28 (two copies); Sept. 4, 11 (two copies), 18 (two copies), 25; Oct. 2, 9, 16 (two copies), 23 (two copies), 30; Nov. 6, 20, 27; Dec. 4, 11, 18, 25
    - 1921, Jan. 1, 22, 29; Feb. 5, 12, 26; March 5, 12, 19; April 9, 30; May 7 (two copies), 14, 21 (two copies), 28; June 4, 11, 18, 25; July 2, 9, 15, 30; Aug. 6, 13; Sept. 3, 10, 17; Oct. 15, 22, 29; Nov. 12 (two copies), 19
    - 1922, Feb. 11, 18, 25; March 4, 11, 25; April 1, 8, 15, 22, 29; May 3, 6, 13, 20, 27; June 24; July 1, 15, 22, 29; Aug. 5, 19; Sept. 2; Oct. 14
  - Lucha Social, Barcelona. 1925, Jan. 8
  - Luz!!!, Barcelona. 1924, April 26; May 3
  - Mundo Obrero (Comision Politica del Partido Comunista Espanol), Madrid. 1963, Dec.
  - La Rivoluzione Spagnola (P.O.U.M.), Barcelona. 1937, April 1; May 1
  - El Socialista (Partido Socialista Obrero Espanol), Paris. 1949, Sept. 15; 1950, April 13; May 11; 1951, Dec. 20
  - Solidaridad Obrera (CNT-AIT), Barcelona. 1937, Feb. 4; Sept. 14
  - Solidaridad Obrera (CNT-AIT), Paris. 1960, Sept. 22
  - Treball (Partit Socialista Unificat de Catalunya), Barcelona. 1937, July 27
- MEMORABILIA, 1950-1952
  - Two oversize scrapbooks containing printed copies of articles by Maurin published under his pen name of Julio Antonio (Roy), 1950-1952 (Box 32 on shelf)